Puerto Rican Oral History Project records 1976.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Rodriguez, Ramon, 1974 October 29; 1976.001.058
  Bonilla, Carmelita, 1908-; Colon, Jesus, 1901-1974; Rodriguez, Ramon, 1902-; Tapia, Carlos; Weber, Louis; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Columbia Heights (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Santiago, Georgina, 1974 November 22; 1976.001.059
  Georgina Santiago was born in Coamo, Puerto Rico in 1890. She arrived in Brooklyn in April 1925 aboard the steamship San Lorenzo, and continued to reside in the borough at the time of the interview in 1974. Her husband Ramon Santiago - who died in 1944 - was a pioneering "Bodeguero" who opened up grocery stores that catered to the growing Spanish-speaking and Latin American population. He was also considered a benefactor among the Puerto Rican community. Santiago spent her first years in Brooklyn living in the Downtown area, later moving to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Williamsburg - near the family store, which was located at the corner of Flushing Avenue and Bedford Avenue - and then a few blocks away in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bedford-Stuyvesant.
  In the interview, Georgina Santiago shares her experiences while living and raising a family in the Downtown Brooklyn area. She discusses the ethnic makeup of the neighborhood, as well as her husband Ramon Santiago's role in the community. She also discusses the bodega her husband opened on Bedford Avenue and Flushing Avenue - which was one of the first in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. The challenge of raising a family, making ends meet, and running a business during the Great Depression of the 1930s is also covered. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Santiago, Georgina, 1890-; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Work environment |z United States; World War, 1939-1945
- Sepulveda, Ernesto, 1974 November 6; 1976.001.060
  Ernesto Sepúlveda arrived in Brooklyn in 1926 at age twenty-two and had resided there consistently when this interview took place in 1974. He married in 1925 and was a father to a daughter and son by 1930. He attained a tenth-grade level education. Sepúlveda had some training as an auto mechanic and owned a grocery store before he became a retiree. Ernesto Sepúlveda died a Brooklyn resident in August, 1982.
  In the interview, Ernesto Sepúlveda recalls factory conditions in Brooklyn, circa 1930. He discusses political clubs such as Casino Puertorriqueño and Acto Civico. Sepúlveda looks back on 1934, when the first political club for Puerto Ricans in New York was established and he was their first member. He cites leading Puerto Rican personalities, among them Carlos Tapia and Louis Weber. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Sepulveda, Ernesto, 1903-; Tapia, Carlos; Weber, Louis; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Markets |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs
- Simmons, Rafaela, 1974 November 15; 1976.001.061
  Born circa 1903 in Puerto Rico, Rafaela Simmons arrived in Brooklyn in 1928 and remained a resident throughout her life. She had attained a second-grade education and made a living with her sewing machine training. In 1974, Simmons was retired. Rafaela Simmons died in September, 1984.
  In the interview, Rafaela Simmons remembers her experiences when she was new to Brooklyn and to the needle trade of the Puerto Rican community, circa 1930s. She relates her story of joining the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) in 1934. Simmons also describes the Williamsburg community of Puerto Ricans in the mid-twentieth century. A persistent audiotape anomaly has obscured this sound recording. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Simmons, Rafaela, 1903-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic relations; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Torres, Clemente, 1974 November 20; 1976.001.062
  Born in Puerto Rico in 1905, Clemente Torres arrived in Brooklyn in 1927 and remained a resident into the mid-1970s. He was employed by the United States Postal Service as a postal clerk for thirty years and was retired by 1974. Torres relocated to Aguadilla, Puerto Rico for several of his remaining years. Clemente Torres died in April, 1994.
  In the interview, Clemente Torres describes the Borough Hall neighborhood of Brooklyn, circa 1930s. He mentions several political organizations by name, focusing on La Union Civica Puertorriqueña, located on Washington Street, Brooklyn, and founded between 1935 and 1936. Torres reflects on factory conditions and overall employment status for Puerto Ricans in mid-twentieth century New York City. He remembers Carlos Tapia and the activities that made Tapia a paternal figure to Brooklyn's Puerto Rican community. A misplaced microphone obscured the early minutes of this sound recording. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Torres, Clemente, 1905-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Language; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York
- Torres, Olga, 1974 August 21; 1976.001.063
  Olga Torres arrived in Brooklyn in 1926 at the age of nine. She resided there consistently until 1982. She had a high school diploma and was a registered nurse, working as a medical assistant. Divorced and the mother of two children (one of whom is interviewer John D. Vazquez), Torres stayed well-informed and self-educated into her sixties and seventies.
  In the interview, Olga Torres describes the neighborhood of Downtown Brooklyn in the 1930s and 1940s, especially Gold, High, and Sands Streets. She points out the ethnic distribution of pupils and teachers at Public School No. 12. She recalls the influence of well-known community personality Sister Carmelita, and reveals the origins of the first Puerto Rican gangs, including "Conmigo no te metas." Torres also refers to the American experience of early Puerto Rican immigrants, as well as the policy racket or numbers game linking the community and political leaders. Interview conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Bonilla, Carmelita, 1908-; Torres, Olga, 1917-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Rico
- Vazquez, Juan, 1973 November 5; 1976.001.064
  Juan M. Vázquez was born in Puerto Rico in 1912. He immigrated to the United States in 1929, arriving in Brooklyn. In 1955, after twenty-five years of laboring in the borough's factories, he opened a grocery store, and for decades afterward worked as the owner/operator. By 1974, Vázquez had made Brooklyn his permanent home. He was a father of four; among them sociologist and this project's interviewer John D. Vazquez.
  In the interview, Juan M. Vázquez offers a very succinct personal history; including his work experience and social involvement, starting with his 1929 arrival in Brooklyn. He describes both the relatively small and tight-knit pre-World War II Puerto Rican community of New York City, as well as socializing within the city's ethnic milieu of Southern and Eastern European immigrants. Early and mid-20th century Puerto Rican political and social clubs - as well as Spanish-language news media - are also touched on. Vázquez anticipates that he would spend the rest of his days in the borough rather than returning to Puerto Rico. Interview conducted by Monte Rivera.
  El Diario de Nueva York.; La Prensa Newspaper, Inc..; Vazquez, Juan, Sr., 1912-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Velazquez, Carolina, 1974 August 6; 1976.001.065
  Carolina Velázquez was born in Arroyo, Puerto Rico and moved to New York in 1930 after a week-long journey aboard the Ponce ship. Velázquez moved to Brooklyn with her sister, leaving her three siblings in Puerto Rico. She worked as a house cleaner and lampshade factory worker in Brooklyn. Velázquez married and had two children. During this time, she babysat children in her home and returned to work after her children were old enough. She became a widow when her children were still young. She was the recipient of several public assistance programs such as Welfare, Social Security, and Medicare.
  In this interview, Carolina Velázquez narrates her life in Arroyo, Puerto Rico, her reasons for migrating to New York, her voyage to New York, and her first years in Brooklyn. Velázquez reflects on discrimination faced by Puerto Ricans and other Latinos and shares her opinion on bilingual education. She compares the Puerto Rican community in the 1930s and 1940s to the Puerto Rican community in the 1970s and lists some of the social issues present at the time of the 1974 interview. Velázquez also opines on the independence movement in Puerto Rico and talks about voter registration processes in the 1930s. Interview in English and Spanish conducted by Mayda Cortiella.
  New York (N.Y.). Department of Public Welfare.; Tapia, Carlos; Velazquez, Carolina, 1911-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Depressions |y 1929; Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |x Housing |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Language; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Voter registration
- Vice, Celia Maria, 1974 August 7; 1976.001.066
  Celia Maria Vice was born in Guayanilla, Puerto Rico in 1913. She arrived in Brooklyn at Pier Nine aboard a steam ship, and resided with her family in the Brooklyn neighborhoods of DUMBO and Vinegar Hill, later moving to the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Williamsburg and Bedford-Stuyvesant (where she lived at the time of the interview in 1974). Vice worked several factory and office jobs - including a position at a defense plant during World War II - before going into business for herself. She performed services including translating, as well as selling real estate - as the first Puerto Rican woman broker in Brooklyn - and insurance. She also remained extremely active in the community during her lifetime as a member of multiple citywide committees, including the New York City Human Rights Commission. Vice helped found a number of civic and cultural entities including the Puerto Rican Heritage Publishing Company, the Fernando Sierra Vardeci Independent Democratic Club, and el Museo del Barrio (a community museum) and was the first Latina grand marshal of the Puerto Rican Day Parade. She relocated back to Puerto Rico in 1979, establishing the Kiosko Cultural in the Plaza de Las Americas. Celia Maria Vice died in 1993.
  In the interview, Celia Vice discusses the social and economic situation for Puerto Ricans - and New Yorkers in general - during the 1920s and 1930s. She touches on work, health and housing conditions, as well as describes the ethnic composition of Downtown Brooklyn and its surrounding waterfront, which was the initial area of settlement for Brooklyn's Puerto Rican community. Vice provides detailed information on the cohesion, self-sustainability, and ultimate socioeconomic progress of Brooklyn's early Puerto Rican migrants; including descriptions of mutual aid, religion, child development, education, work ethic, cultural heritage and community organizing. Interview conducted by Ms. Torres and Ms. Ruiz.
  Vice, Celia M., 1913-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Villa, Betty, 1974 September 11; 1976.001.067
  Born in 1922, Betty Villa (one of the few narrators in this collection to be a borough native) was raised in the Downtown section of Brooklyn. She later lived between the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Williamsburg and Bedford-Stuyvesant, before relocating to Carolina, Puerto Rico in the 1960s. While growing up in the 1920s and 1930s she experienced racial discrimination firsthand, both from individuals and institutions. Despite this, she made friends of all ethnic stripes - even once marching in the Saint Patrick's Day Parade - and attended Brooklyn College before joining the workforce. She was the mother of three children, as well as an activist in civic, political, and mutual aid organizations throughout her life.
  In the interview, Betty Villa describes the Downtown Brooklyn area of the 1920 and 1930s. She gives firsthand information on figures such as Sister Carmelita Bonilla, Celia Vice, Luis Hernández, and Antonia Denis, as well as an account of Reverend W.E. Davenport (a Brooklyn philanthropist who was somewhat active in the Eugenics movement). She refers to the first church serving Spanish-speaking Catholics in Brooklyn, Our Lady of Pilar. Villa recalls both her encounters with racism, as well as friendships across ethnic and racial lines. Villa also discusses Puerto Rican identity, politics, and society, as well as the experience of reverse migration to Puerto Rico from New York. Interview conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Bonilla, Carmelita, 1908-; Vice, Celia M., 1913-; Villa, Betty, 1919-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civic leaders |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z New York; Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Segregation |z United States |x History; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Series 2: Oral Histories, 1975
- Series 3: Oral History Transcripts, Bulk, 1973-1975; 1973-1975, 1983
- Series 4: Puerto Rican Community, Bulk, 1973-1975; 1960-1983
- Series 5: Administrative Materials, Bulk, 1973-1975; 1968-1984